I'm sorry to sour the mood, Shinichi, but…
Nie chcę psuć ci humoru, ale…
No way. You must be kidding.
Niemożliwe.
We need to start running right now.
Musimy uciekać.
Are you sure it's him?
To na pewno on?
These wavelengths are too powerful to come from some lackey.
Sygnał jest zbyt potężny, by go z kimś pomylić.
And given the speed of his approach, I'd say he's in a car.
Zbliża się szybko, zapewne autem.
Take a right at that corner.
Skręć w prawo.
Shit! Now I'm a thief.
Szlag, jestem złodziejem.
Is this the time to whine about it?
To nie pora na żale.
When did you learn to drive, anyway?
Kiedy nauczyłeś się prowadzić?
I mastered Japanese in a single day, you know.
Pamiętaj, że w jeden dzień nauczyłem się japońskiego.
Migi, I have a favor to ask.
Migi, chcę o coś prosić.
Please go somewhere with as few people as possible.
Pojedź na jakieś odludzie.
If we fight him in a city, many people will die.
W mieście mogłyby zginąć niewinne osoby.
Very well.
W porządku.
I've thought of something that's worth a gamble.
Mam pewien pomysł.
AUTHOR: HITOSHI IWAAKI
AUTOR: HITOSHI IWAAKI
QUIESCENCE AND AWAKENING
SEN I PRZEBUDZENIE
Well?
I co?
It didn't work.
Nie udało się.
He's alive.
Żyje.
He's tough.
Twardy jest.
Let's go.
Chodź.
Go where?
Dokąd?
Let's run.
Uciekamy.
All right, stop.
Zatrzymaj się.
Why are we stopping?
Dlaczego?
We can't afford to waste time here!
Nie mamy czasu do stracenia.
Calm down.
Uspokój się.
Let's strategize until he shows up.
Zastanówmy się nad strategią.
Strategize?
Nad strategią?
We might be minutes away from being chopped up!
Zaraz potnie nas na kawałki.
Shinichi.
Shinichi.
I understand how you feel.
Rozumiem, co czujesz.
Anyone would fear death.
Wszyscy boją się śmierci.
I'm afraid as well.
Ja również.
However, this is our moment of truth!
Ale to nasza chwila prawdy.
You have a strength normal humans don't have.
Jest w tobie siła, której nie posiadają zwyczajni ludzie.
You can be calm, no matter what the circumstance.
Potrafisz zachować spokój we wszelkich okolicznościach.
Now, put your hand on your chest
Połóż rękę na pierś i oddychaj głęboko.
Good. Well done.
Dobra robota.
Listen.
Posłuchaj.
When it comes to ability, Gotou surpasses us in every way.
Gotou jest od ciebie sprawniejszy w niemal każdym calu.
By simple calculations, our odds of victory might be 0%,
Czysta matematyka daje nam zerowe szanse zwycięstwo.
but that just means we should approach this from a different angle.
Musimy zatem podejść do tego z innej strony.
If we can't win even by working together,
Jeśli nie możemy wygrać, współpracując,
maybe we should try not working together.
może powinniśmy się rozdzielić.
In war, what matters is opportunity, not numbers.
Na wojnie liczy się sposobność, nie liczebność.
Opportunity?
Sposobność?
In your pocket is a lighter I found in the car.
W kieszeni masz zapalniczkę, którą znalazłem w aucie.
They're above.
Są nade mną.
They've spread out among the tree branches to hide.
Skryli się w gałęziach.
How unoriginal.
Nic nowego.
This will be a race against time.
To będzie wyścig z czasem.
To a parasite, the body is our lifeline as well as our greatest weakness.
Ciało jest dla pasożyta źródłem życia, ale i największą słabością.
My cells that have dispersed in your body
Moje komórki, które rozeszły się po twoim ciele,
have been completely integrated and are altered,
są całkowicie zintegrowane i zmodyfikowane,
so, Gotou can't detect them.
więc Gotou ich nie wykryje.
He will come straight for me
Pójdzie prosto na mnie, nie zauważając twojej obecności.
If there is a protracted fight, I will shrivel up and die.
Jeśli walka potrwa zbyt długo, uschnę i umrę.
This is an extremely reckless strategy,
To bardzo ryzykowna strategia,
but that means even Gotou is unlikely to anticipate our strategy.
ale to znaczy, że Gotou nie będzie się jej spodziewał.
What, no counterattack?
Co, nie kontratakujesz?
Where is the human boy?
Gdzie ten chłopak?
If only I can find and destroy the body, I'll win.
Jeśli zniszczę jego ciało, wygram.
His body is protected by semi-hardened parasite cells.
Jego ciało chronią wzmocnione komórki pasożytnicze.
It's unlikely that his entire body is armored,
Zapewne nie pokrywają całego ciała,
but there's no time to find where the chinks are in his armor.
ale nie mamy czasu na szukanie przerw w pancerzu.
The part least likely to be armored
Naszym celem będzie część,
and thus most suitable as a target
która najprawdopodobniej nie jest opancerzona:
is his head.
jego głowa.
Unifying the multiple parasites in his torso and limbs
Zjednoczenie kilku pasożytów w torsie i kończynach
must require a tremendous amount of energy.
musi wymagać ogromnych pokładów energii.
Thus, the "head" has its hands full acting as the control tower.
Głowa jest zapewne przeciążona funkcjami.
If we lop the head off,
Jeśli ją utniemy,
unity will be lost along with his armor,
pancerz zostanie przerwany, a my będziemy mogli zniszczyć jego ciało.
Any time now, Migi!
Jestem gotowy, Migi.
If you don't hurry, you'll…
Musisz się spieszyć!
I will only have one chance!
Mam tylko jedną szansę.
If I am to decapitate Gotou when his power and speed far surpass my own…
Muszę uciąć mu głowę, choć jest ode mnie silniejszy i szybszy.
What is this?
Co jest?
My consciousness is already fading.
Zaczynam słabnąć.
I must hurry!
Muszę się spieszyć. Ale wciąż nie mam dobrej pozycji.
Hey! Listen up!
Słuchaj!
Are you that scared of me?
Aż tak się mnie boisz?
Spreading out in all directions isn't much of a camouflage!
Te gałęzie nie zapewnią ci dobrego kamuflażu.
Use your brains to fight, not run!
Zamiast uciekać, zastanów się, jak walczyć.
Now! Do it!
Teraz!
Was that my voice?
To mój głos?
There!
Tam!
The surface cells will instinctively disengage
Ogień sprawi, że Gotou straci kontrolę nad wierzchnimi komórkami.
and as a result…
A wtedy…
Damn! Not deep enough!
Szlag, nie dość głęboko!
Did we fail?
Nie udało się?
Migi!
Migi!
Stay back, Shinichi!
Nie zbliżaj się!
We failed!
Nie udało się!
Well, this is a surprise. Well done.
A to niespodzianka. Brawo.
Run! Now!
Uciekaj!
-But… -Don't come any closer!
- Ale… - Nie podchodź.
We don't both need to die!
Nie musimy ginąć oboje.
But Migi.
Ale, Migi…
What are you doing? Hurry up and go!
Co robisz? Uciekaj!
Goodbye, Shinichi.
Żegnaj, Shinichi.
This is farewell, Shinichi.
Więcej się nie zobaczymy.
I'm glad I didn't take over your brain when we first met.
Cieszę się, że nie przejąłem twojego mózgu.
Thanks to that, we made many good memories as friends.
Dzięki temu zebraliśmy wiele dobrych wspomnień jako przyjaciele.
I'm fading.
Odchodzę.
I feel oddly sleepy
Robię się śpiący…
yet it's all eclipsed by the feeling that I'm so alone.
i ogrania mnie potworna samotność.
So, this…
A więc to…
is death.
jest śmierć.
Who's there?
Kto tam jest?
Oh, sorry.
Przepraszam.
A… A burglar?
Złodziej?
No!
Nie!
I'm not, but…
Chociaż…
Sure. You can call me that.
można by mnie nim nazwać.
I did try to drink some water without permission, after all.
Chciałem napić się pani wody.
I see.
Rozumiem.
Water isn't free, either.
Za wodę też trzeba płacić.
Sorry.
Przepraszam.
Well…
Dobrze…
I should go.
pójdę już.
I'm sorry for the trouble.
Przepraszam za kłopot.
Hang on a second.
Poczekaj.
Yes?
Tak?
You're hurt.
Jesteś ranny.
Well, no…
Nie…
No, your head.
Mówię o głowie.
You lost your right arm a long time ago, from the looks of it.
Widzę, że rękę straciłeś już dawno temu.
I'm fine.
Nic mi nie jest.
I think the bleeding's already stopped.
Krwawienie już ustało.
Just come in and let me take a look.
Wejdź. Przyjrzę się ranie.
-But… -Hurry up!
- Ale… - No chodźże!
A burglar wouldn't be this polite.
Złodziej nie byłby taki kulturalny.
Besides, you look like you've been crying.
Zresztą wyglądasz, jakbyś płakał.
I worked in retail for a long time.
Długo pracowałam w handlu.
I can tell a lot about a person from just one look.
Wystarczy mi jedno spojrzenie, by poznać się na człowieku.
This injury wasn't from a fair fight, was it? You were bullied.
To nie była równa walka, prawda? Zaatakował cię ktoś potężniejszy.
The cut's pretty deep.
Głęboka rana.
Some people in this world do terrible things.
Ludzie potrafią robić straszne rzeczy.
I didn't expect so much kindness from a complete stranger.
Nie spodziewałem się aż takiej dobroci.
Thank you for everything.
Dziękuję za wszystko.
Stay the night.
Zostań na noc.
I couldn't possibly.
Nie mógłbym.
Where do you expect to go this late at night?
A dokąd pójdziesz o tej porze?
There are no hotels around here!
W pobliżu nie ma hotelów.
Do you live here by yourself, Granny?
Mieszka tu pani sama?
I don't have any grandchildren your age.
Nie mam wnuków w twoim wieku.
-Auntie? -I don't have any nephews, either.
- A… - Siostrzeńców też nie mam.
My name is Mitsuyo.
Nazywam się Mitsuyo.
I'm sorry.
Przepraszam.
I'm Izumi Shinichi.
Jestem Izumi Shinichi.
Shinichi, eh?
Shinichi, co?
Shin-chan, then.
Będę mówić ci Shin-chan.
Sorry for making you help with the shopping.
Wybacz, że obarczam cię tymi zakupami.
Oh, no problem.
Żaden problem. Cieszę się, że mogę coś zrobić.
Let's just say you're my nephew.
Mówmy ludziom, że jesteś moim siostrzeńcem.
Nephew?
Siostrzeńcem?
Strange things have been happening around here lately.
Działy się tu ostatnio dziwne rzeczy.
They're suspicious of outsiders.
Ludzie przestali ufać obcym.
This is what I was talking about.
O tym mówiłam.
Someone keeps dumping truckloads of garbage without permission.
Ktoś wyrzuca tu bez pozwolenia tony śmieci.
One time, it caught fire and nearly set the entire mountain ablaze.
Raz zapłonęły i niemal spaliła się cała góra.
I know they say big cities are running out of landfills,
Wiem, że w dużych miastach nie ma już gdzie składować śmieci,
but this is a bit much, don't you think?
ale to już przesada.
Yes.
Racja.
Those of us who live around here
Nasza trójka, która tu mieszka,
have been keeping watch day and night,
pilnowała tego miejsca dzień i noc,
but they're no-shows when we do keep watch
ale nikt się nie pokazał.
and come the one day we sleep.
Czekają, aż zaśniemy.
Mitsuyo-san had a sharp tongue, but she was kindhearted.
Mitsuyo-san miała cięty język, ale dobre serce.
Whenever I tried to thank her and leave,
Kiedy próbowałem podziękować i odejść,
she'd stop me with a machine gun barrage of conversation.
zatrzymywała mnie rozmową.
With Migi gone,
Po odejściu Migiego
I had no idea what to do next.
nie miałem pojęcia, co robić.
I ended up staying several days,
Zostałem na kilka dni,
but I can't impose on her forever.
ale nie mogłem narzucać się tak bez końca.
I should go home tomorrow and tell Dad everything.
Powinienem wrócić do domu i powiedzieć wszystko tacie.
About why I lost my right arm.
O tym, dlaczego straciłem rękę.
About how I had a friend named Migi.
O moim przyjacielu o imieniu Migi.
About the day Migi first showed up in my life.
O tym, jak Migi pojawił się w moim życiu.
About the days we spent together.
O naszych wspólnych dniach.
And about how great a guy he was.
O tym, jaki był wspaniały.
To save my life, he…
Uratował mi życie.
His intelligence, his courage.
Jego inteligencja, odwaga…
I can't even hope to come close to him in any way.
Nie mogę się mu równać.
He is a true hero!
To prawdziwy bohater.
Where am I?
Gdzie ja jestem?
I think I've been here before.
Chyba już tu byłem.
What's that?
Co to?
Who are you?
Kim jesteś?
What is it?
Szukasz tu czegoś?
Looking?
Szukam?
Yeah, I'm looking for a friend.
Tak, szukam przyjaciela.
A friend?
Przyjaciela?
What does this friend look like?
Jak wygląda?
I don't really remember.
- Nie pamiętam. - Więc nie mogę ci pomóc.
Hey, wait.
Poczekaj.
I think he looked like you.
Chyba wyglądał tak jak ty.
Right! I remember now!
Tak, już pamiętam.
He…
On…
He died.
zginął.
What? He's dead?
Umarł?
-No, he's alive. -What?
- Nie, on żyje. - Co?
I can tell.
Czuję to.
I actually know his name, too.
Znam nawet jego imię.
His name?
Jego imię?
His name.
Jego imię.
Migi!
Migi!
Some of his cells are still here!
Wciąż mam w sobie jego komórki.
Hey! It's me!
To ja!
Do you recognize me?
Poznajesz mnie?
Keep it down.
Ucisz się.
Go back to sleep.
Wracaj do spania.
It won't work.
To na nic.
Even if he can make a small eye,
To tylko małe oczko.
it's not enough to be capable of thought or speech.
Nie jest w stanie myśleć ani mówić.
Migi.
Migi.
Migi!
Migi!
I see.
Dobrze.
I guess I don't have a choice.
Nie mam wyjścia.
I can't keep you here forever.
Nie mogę cię tu trzymać bez końca.
I don't know how I can ever repay you.
Nie wiem, jak mogę się odwdzięczyć.
What's the matter?
Co tu robicie tak wcześnie?
Hey, you!
Hej, ty! Naprawdę jesteś siostrzeńcem Mitsuyo-san?
What does it matter?
A co za różnica?
He's about to leave.
Właśnie się zbierał.
Not so fast.
Dzieje się tu ostatnio zbyt wiele dziwnych rzeczy.
The illegal trash dumping,
Nielegalny wywóz śmieci,
the car crash between two driver-less vehicles,
kraksa dwóch aut bez kierowców,
and now, murder.
a teraz morderstwo.
What?
Co?
Isn't it always outsiders who commit crimes?
To zawsze sprawka kogoś obcego.
Outsiders like him?
Kogoś takiego jak on.
I told you, that thing was beyond being an outsider.
Tego czegoś nie można nawet nazwać obcym.
-He's been with me the entire time-- -It wasn't human!
- On był ze mną… - To nie był człowiek!
I wasn't just seeing things!
Nie przywidziało mi się.
It was at least three meters tall!
Miał przynajmniej trzy metry!
And its legs! Yeah, it had four front legs alone!
I cztery nogi!
It had more than three eyes, too!
I więcej niż troje oczu!
It's Gotou.
To Gotou.
It has to be!
Na pewno!
Yeah, laugh at me all you want,
Możecie się śmiać,
but see this blood? It's all Kitayama's!
ale spójrzcie, to krew Kitayamy!
So it happened around here?
To było tutaj?
That's right.
Tak.
This is horrible.
To było straszne.
Wait. Something similar's happened before.
Był już taki przypadek.
The Mincemeat Murders?
Tak, morderstwa zmielonego mięsa.
I see.
Rozumiem.
Okay, got it.
W porządku.
A bunch of hunters is going to get together tomorrow,
Jutro zbierze się grupa myśliwych.
so they should be able to take down this "monster" then.
Dopadną tego potwora.
Hunting rifles won't be enough to take him down.
Ich broń to na niego za mało.
"Him"?
Co?
You know the monster?
Ty znasz tego potwora?
He's here because he's after me.
Jest tu, bo chce mnie dopaść.
To kill me.
Zabić.
Stop talking nonsense.
Nie gadaj bzdur.
This is my fault!
To moja wina.
I brought him here!
Ja go tu sprowadziłem.
And someone was killed!
I ktoś przez to zginął.
Many more will die tomorrow if I don't do something!
Jeśli czegoś nie zrobię, jutro zginą kolejne osoby.
Shin-chan.
Shin-chan.
I just wanted to keep myself alive.
Chciałem tylko przeżyć.
Whatever it took.
Za wszelką cenę.
Friends have died for me, too.
Ginęli za mnie przyjaciele.
But I can't just keep running away on my own.
Nie mogę tak uciec?
Why not?
Dlaczego nie?
Why not live?
Żyj.
Why not run?
Ucieknij.
Run if it's only to save your own life.
Ucieknij, jeśli to ocali ci życie.
It's nothing to be ashamed of.
To nie powód do wstydu.
Mitsuyo-san, I haven't done everything I can just yet!
Nie zrobiłem jeszcze wszystkiego, na co mnie stać.
I have to make use of my life before a group of people
Muszę coś zrobić,
You idiot! Cut the bullshit!
Idioto, zamknij się!
Make use of your life?
Co ty gadasz?
How dare you speak so lightly of your own life?
Nie lekceważ swojego życia.
Who do you think you are?
Za kogo ty się masz?
Use your life?
Chcesz poświęcić swoje życie? Bez żartów!
What does a snot-nosed brat like you expect to do?
Co może zrobić taki smarkacz jak ty?
Look, I don't know your story,
Nie znam twojej historii,
but you should just let adults handle this sort of thing.
ale pozwól, by zajęli się tym dorośli.
You're still leaving?
Naprawdę odchodzisz?
Don't you have someone in your life you care about?
Nie masz w życiu nikogo bliskiego?
Even if it's a stranger, once I come to know them,
Kiedy poznam kogoś lepiej, nie potrafię się od niego odwrócić.
That's what it means to be human.
Na tym polega bycie człowiekiem.
But you…
Posłuchaj…
I don't know how much time you have left,
nie wiem, ile zostało ci czasu,
but give some thought to as many things, as many ideas
ale przemyśl to jeszcze.
as you can come up with.
Przemyśl to dobrze.
If you throw everything away, that's the end.
Jeśli się poddasz, to już koniec.
Don't give up, no matter what, and be flexible.
Więc walcz i pamiętaj, że zawsze jest jakieś rozwiązanie.
Wait.
Poczekaj.
Isn't there something useful you can take with you?
Może weź coś ze sobą.
Like a weapon?
Jakąś broń.
This, then.
Wezmę to.
What, that? It's all rusty.
Jest cały zardzewiały.
But I guess it's better than nothing.
Ale lepsze to niż nic.
Dear.
Najdroższy.
Please keep him safe.
Czuwaj nad nim.
If Gotou's adopted a totally different human appearance,
Jeśli Gotou całkowicie zmienił wygląd,
there'll be no way for me to recognize him.
nie rozpoznam go.
But I'll cross that bridge when I come to it!
Ale nie wyprzedzajmy faktów!
Next time, "Life and Oath."
Następny odcinek: „Życie i przysięga”.